Wonder by RJ Palacio ordinary I KNOW I’M not an ordinary 10 year old I
mean, sure, I do ordinary things. I eat ice
cream. I ride my bike. I play ball. I have an XBox. Stuff like that makes me
ordinary. I guess.
And I feel ordinary. Inside.
But I know ordinary kids don’t make other ordinary kids run away screaming in playgrounds.
I know ordinary kids don’t get stared at wherever they go.
If I found a magic lamp and I could have
one wish, I would wish that I had a normal face that no one ever noticed at
all. I would wish that I could walk down the street without people seeing me and
then doing that look away thing.
Here’s what I think: the only reason I’m
not ordinary is that no one else sees me that way.
But I’m kind of used to how I look by now.
I know how to pretend I don’t see the faces people make.
We’ve all gotten pretty good at that sort of thing: me, Mom and Dad, Via.
Actually, I take that back: Via’s not so good at it.
She can get really annoyed when people do something rude. Like, for instance, one
time in the playground some older kids made some noises. I didn't even know what
the noises were exactly because I didn’t hear them myself, but Via heard and she
just started yelling at the kids. That’s the way she is. I’m not that way
Leah doesn’t see me as ordinary. She says she does, but if I were ordinary, she
wouldn’t feel like she needs to protect me as much.
And Mom and Dad don’t see me as ordinary, either. They see me as extraordinary. I
think the only person in the world who realizes how ordinary I am is me.
My name is August, by the way.
I won’t describe what I look like.
Whatever you’re thinking probably worse why I didn't go to school NEXT WEEK I start fifth grade.
Since I’ve never been to a real school before, I am pretty much totally and
completely petrified.
People think I haven’t gone to school because of the way I look, but it’s not
that. It’s because of all the surgeries I’ve had 27 since I was born.
The bigger ones happened before I was even four years old, so I don’t remember those.
But I’ve had two or three surgeries every year since then (some big, some
small), and because I’m little for my age, and I have some other medical mysteries
that doctors never really figured out, I used to get sick a lot.
That’s why my parents decided it was better if I didn’t go to school.
I’m much stronger now, though. The last surgery I had was eight months ago, and I
probably won’t have to have any more for another couple of years.
Mom homeschools me.
She used to be a children's book illustrator.
She draws really great fairies and mermaids. Her boy stuff isn’t so hot,
though. She once tried to draw me a Darth Vader, but it ended up looking like some
weird mushroom-shaped robot.
I haven’t seen her draw anything in a long time. I think she’s too busy taking
care of me and Via.
I can’t say I always wanted to go to school because that wouldn’t be exactly
true. What I wanted was to go to school then only if I could be like every other
kid going to school. Have lots of friends and hang out after school and stuff like that.
I have a few really good friends now.
Christopher is my best friend, followed by Zachary and Alex. We’ve known each
other since we were babies. And since they’ve always known me the way I am,
they’re used to me. When we were little, we used to have play dates all the time,
but then Christopher moved to Bridgeport in Connecticut. That’s more than an hour
away from where I live in North River Heights, which is at the top tip of
Manhattan. And Zachary and Alex started going to school.
It’s funny: even though Christopher’s the one who moved far away, I still see him
more than I see Zachary and Alex.
They have all these new friends now. If we bump into each other on the street,
they’re still nice to me, though. They always say hello.
I have other friends, too, but not as good as Christopher and Zach and Alex were.
For instance Zach and Alex always invited me to their birthday parties
when we were little, but Joel and Eamon and Gabe never did.
Emma invited me once, but I haven’t seen her in a long time. And, of course, I
always go to Christopher’s birthday.
Maybe I’m making too big a deal about birthday parties how I came to life
I LIKE WHEN Mom tells this story because it makes me laugh so much. It’s not funny
in a way a joke is funny, but when Mom
tells it V and I just start cracking up.
So when I was in my mom’s stomach, no one
had any idea I would come out looking the way I look.
Mom had had Via four years before, and that had been such a “walk in the
park” (Mom’s expression) that there was no reason to run any special tests. About
two months before I was born, the doctors realized there was something wrong with
my face, but they didn’t think it was
going to be bad. They told Mom and Dad I had a cleft palate and some other stuff
going on. They called it “small anomalies.” There were two nurses in the delivery
room the night I was born.
One was very nice and sweet. The other one, Mom said, did not seem at all nice or
sweet. She had very big arms and (here comes the funny part),
she kept farting. Like, she’d bring Mom some ice chips, and then fart. She’d check
Mom’s blood pressure, and fart.
Mom says it was unbelievable because the nurse never even said excuse me!
Meanwhile, Mom’s regular doctor wasn’t on duty that night, so Mom got stuck with
this cranky kid doctor she and Dad nicknamed Doogie after some old TV show or something
(they didn’t actually call him that to his face).
But Mom says that even though everyone in the room was kind of grumpy, Dad kept
making her laugh all night long.
When I came out of Mom’s stomach, she said the whole room got very quiet. Mom
didn’t even get a chance to look at me because the nice nurse immediately
rushed me out of the room that was in such a hurry to follow her
that he dropped the video camera, which broke into a million pieces. And then Mom
got very upset and tried to get out of bed to see where they were going, but the
farting nurse put her very big arms on Mom to keep her down in the bed. They
were practically fighting, because Mom was hysterical and the farting nurse was
yelling at her to stay calm, and then they both started screaming for the
doctor. But guess what? He had fainted!
Right on the floor!
So when the farting nurse saw that he had fainted, she started pushing him with
her foot to get him to wake up, yelling at him the whole time: “What kind of
doctor are you? What kind of doctor are you? Get up! Get up!”
And then all of a sudden she let out the biggest, loudest, smelliest fart in the
history of farts.
Mom thinks it was actually the fart that finally woke the doctor up.
Anyway, when Mom tells this story, she acts out all the parts— —including the
farting noises— —and it is so, so, so, so so so funny!
Mom says the farty nurse turned out to be a very nice woman.
She stayed with Mom the whole time.
Didn’t leave her side even after Dad came back and the doctors told them how
sick I was. Mom remembers exactly what the nurse whispered in her ear when the
doctor told her I probably wouldn’t live through the night: “Everyone born of God overcometh the
world.” And the next day, after I had lived through the night, it was that nurse who
held Mom’s hand when they brought her to meet me for the first time.
Mom says by then they had told her all about me. She had been preparing herself
for the scene of me. But she says that when she looked down into my tiny mushed
up face for the first time, all she could see was how pretty my eyes
were. Mom is beautiful, by the way. And that is handsome. Via is pretty. In case
you were wondering Christopher's house I WAS REALLY bummed when Christopher
moved away three years ago. We were both around seven then. We used to spend hours
playing with our Star Wars action figures and dueling with our lightsabers.
I miss that.
Last spring we drove over to Christopher’s house in Bridgeport.
Me and Christopher were looking for snacks in the kitchen, and I heard Mom
talking to Lisa, Christopher’s mom, about my going to school in the fall. I had
never, ever heard her mention school before.
“What are you talking about?” I said. Mom looks surprised, like she hadn’t meant
for me to hear that. “You should tell him what you’ve been thinking, Isabel,” Dad
said. He was on the other side of the living room talking to Christopher’s dad.
“We should talk about this later,” said Mom.
“No, I want to know what you were talking about,” I answered.
“Don’t you think you’re ready for school Augie Mom said.
“No,” I said. “I don’t, either,” said Dad.
“Then that’s it, case closed,” I said, shrugging, and I sat in her lap like I
was a baby.
“I just think you need to learn more than
I can teach you,” Mom said. “I mean, come on, Auggie, you know how bad I am at
fractions!” “What school?” I said. I already felt like crying beat your Prep. Right by us.”
“Wow, that’s a great school Augie said Lisa Patty my knee or not via school?” I said.
“That’s too big,” Mom answered. “I don’t think that would be a good fit for you.”
“I don’t want to,” I said.
I admit: I made my voice sound a little babyish.
“You don’t have to do anything you don’t want to do,” Dad said, coming over and
lifting me out of Mom’s lap. He carried
me over to sit on his lap on the other
side of the sofa. “We won’t make you do anything you don’t want to do.”
“But it would be good for him, Nate,” Mom said.
“Not if he doesn’t want to answer Dad, looking at me.
“Not if he’s not ready.” I saw Mom look at Lisa, who reached over
and squeezed her hand.
“You guys will figure it out,” she said to Mom. “You always have.”
“Let’s just talk about it later,” said Mom.
I could tell she and Dad were going to get in a fight about it.
I want a Dad to win the fight.
Though a part of me knew Mom was right.
And the truth is, she really was terrible at fractions foreign
[Music]
foreign